- [Narrator] Good afternoon,
we begin with breaking news.
- An explosion on an
oil drilling platform.
- [Narrator] In the Gulf of Mexico.
- [Narrator] On April 20th,
2010, an explosion occurred
on the Deep Water Horizon oil platform.
- The worst oil spill in U.S. history.
- [Narrator] You could see
that floating oil slick
from space every day.
- [Narrator] And what followed
was millions of gallons
of oils spilling
uncontrollably into the ocean.
- [Narrator] It is almost
unthinkable, isn't it?
- This is a battle we're
waging against an oil spill
that is assaulting our
shores and our citizens.
- [Narrator] This video tells the story
of the race to stop that spill,
how engineers tried to pluck
a hole over 5,000 feet deep under water,
and I wanted to know just how
much oil was actually lost
in the disaster, and try different methods
to better visualize the
sheer amount of loss
beyond just numbers alone.
This is Deepwater Horizon Visualized.
To visualize just how
much oil was spilled,
we first need some sort
of measuring container,
but ordinary containers won't do,
so instead we will be using
the Empire State Building
in New York City.
Theoretically, it can hold up
to 277 million gallons of oil,
but to start off, our container is empty
as we look back to the
evening of the disaster.
On the evening of April 20th, 2010,
everything still seems
normal on Deepwater Horizon
with workers busy
finishing up the borehole.
What many may not know is
that the Deepwater Horizon rig
isn't actually an oil platform
designed for extraction.
Instead, it is a drilling
rig used on new sites.
Its job is to create the initial borehole,
and install a wellhead on the sea floor,
and once that is done, it'll move on
and another platform will take over
for the actual extraction of oil.
The well itself is finished.
The natural oil and gas
reservoir has been reached,
and all that's left to
do now is create a seal,
so that Deepwater Horizon
can finally leave,
so that a smaller, less
costly rig can take its place.
For this transition, it
is important that the well
is completely closed off,
and so the crew members
are carrying out a test to make
sure that the well is ready
to be temporarily abandoned for
the transition between rigs.
But all of the sudden the
crew notices a huge spike
in pressure readings.
This is bad because it usually indicates
that oil and gas has
unexpectedly entered the well.
The crew then runs the
same pressure test again,
but it is the same result.
This is especially bad news
for oil giant, bp
considering it costs them
more than a million dollars
a day to operate the rig.
And at this point, Deepwater Horizon
is already more than six
weeks behind schedule
to move to its next location.
Economic pressures that may have resulted
in a culture of negligence.
Despite the alarming pressure readings,
the crew decides to carry on.
And then just before 10:00 p.m.
those still awake on board of
Deepwater Horizon are shocked
when a geyser of mud and
sea water begins gushing out
of the well and showering the rig.
Before anyone can grasp
what is even happening,
the worst case scenario occurs,
oil and gas escapes from
the wellhead and rushes up
to the platform where the gas explodes.
- [News Reporter] We are
looking at new pictures
from the scene.
The Coast Guard says
the explosion happened
around 10 o'clock last night.
- There's a desperate search
in the Gulf of Mexico.
- For 11 people who were
on a drilling platform
when it exploded.
- [Narrator] Of the 126
personnel initially on board
of Deepwater Horizon, 115 are rescued,
but 11 men are missing.
- The rig is still burning out of control.
- [News Reporter] We have
covered approximately 1,940
square miles of search area.
- [Narrator] A desperate
search is carried out
for the missing men, but
as the evening rolls over
into the next day and
the sun begins to rise,
it isn't looking good.
By day three of scouring the
Gulf and still no sign of them,
the search is called off.
Tragically, all 11 men were
presumed to be near the blast
and were unable to escape in time.
The fate of Deepwater Horizon
is looking just as grim.
Emergency responders attempt
to put out the blaze,
but this is made complicated
by its remote location
in the Gulf of Mexico, as well as oil
from the well continually
fueling the fire.
- [Narrator] It was... You cannot imagine
how enormous this this rig is, anyway.
It's the size of two or
three football fields.
- [Narrator] There is little
anyone can realistically do
and any attempt to douse the
enormous fire is in vain.
And while creaking and groaning,
the rig finally begins
to tilt into the gulf.
After two days of burning,
it only takes minutes
for Deepwater Horizon to slip
beneath the water surface
and sink to the bottom of the sea.
The fires come to an end,
and yet it doesn't mark
the end of the disaster.
In fact, this was still just a beginning
because deep down below,
the well Deepwater Horizon had drilled
is now leaking into the Gulf,
starting to fill our
measuring container with oil.
Initially, bp reported
that no oil was escaping into the sea,
but this was corrected
just a few days later
when a new report came out
that there was indeed a leak.
As the extent of the spill
became more apparent,
bp began feeling the immense pressure
to close the leak as soon as possible.
And our first order of business
is to send a remote operated vehicle down
to the well itself.
This vehicle should provide answers.
and help them figure out
where exactly the oil
is leaking from.
Every well drilled has a
very large complex structure
installed on the sea floor
called a blowout preventer
or BOP for short.
The drill pipe from the rig
to the well must run through the BOP,
which is a safeguard to
prevent uncontrolled oil
and gas from traveling up the
drill pipe and to the rig.
Essentially the BOP is there
to prevent exactly what
happened here, a blowout.
To do so, the BOP has two
systems that can be used
to close a well, pipe ramps
which are heavy metal blocks
that can clamp together to stop the flow.
And annular preventers
that close the pipe using a rubber seal.
And on the day of the accident,
crew members on the
Deepwater Horizon platform
did actually deploy both systems
within the BOP in an effort
to close the well.
However, because these systems
were activated too late,
they didn't work as intended.
Oil and gas had already
entered the pipe above the BOP,
meaning there was nothing left to stop it
from reaching the rig.
In theory, this also should
have been preventable
as there was one final
fail safe within the BOP
that should have been
engaged to close the well.
The Blind Shear Ram.
Once activated, the Blind Shear
Ram uses a sharp metal blade
to cut the pipe and form a seal.
Crew members later reported
that they tried to activate
the Blind Shear Ram after the explosions,
but because they had lost
power, the switch didn't work.
However, this also shouldn't
have mattered as the BOP
is designed with a fail safe mechanism
to automatically engage
the Blind Shear Ram
if it loses connection with the rig,
such as in the case of a power outage.
Why this didn't work is
a mystery to the experts,
and something the ROV will study.
And once they are able to reach the BOP,
a devastating site is waiting for them.
The crews says that the
Blind Shear Ram did engage,
but because the pipe had buckled,
it did not cut the pipe as it should have.
Rather, the Ram punctured the pipe,
thereby making things even worse
and allowing a large volume
of oil and gas to escape.
Now aware of the full
extent of the problem,
it was time to come up with a plan.
The only guaranteed way
to permanently seal the
well will be by drilling
a completely new borehole that intersects
with the existing one.
That way mud and cement can be pumped
through the new entrance to seal the leak,
eventually choking the flow
of oil and gas completely.
The crew begins drilling this relief well
12 days after the explosion,
and a week later they
begin drilling a second one
just in case the first should fail.
But this process will take months,
and every day until then, the
well will still be leaking,
causing massive environmental damage
and filling up our container
of the Empire State Building.
Therefore, experts head
to the drawing board
to figure out alternative solutions
that could lead to a faster result,
and they come up with an idea.
What if they could simply cover the leak
with some sort of dome.
A structure like that exists
and it is called the Cofferdam,
a large steel and concrete structure,
weighing nearly 100 metric tons.
A solution that has never
been tried before this deep.
The Cofferdam is designed
with an opening on the side,
so that it can be lifted
over the broken pipe
and on the walls of the
Cofferdam there are four flaps.
These are there in case
the dam starts sinking
into the ocean mud to prevent
it from sinking too low.
If everything goes to plan,
most of the oil would rush up,
and flow through a pipe
inserted into a smaller opening
at the top of the dome.
And from there the oil
would be directed up
to a tanker ship.
To turn this plan into reality,
crew members are slowly getting to work,
lowering the Cofferdam into the gulf,
but almost immediately there is a problem.
As the Cofferdam descends
into the colder high pressure depths,
the gas escaping from the well reacts
with the surrounding water,
and forms methane hydrates,
essentially ice crystals that
block the opening at the top
of the dome.
And with the opening frozen off,
the oil and gas inside the
dome now has nowhere to escape
and therefore the entire Cofferdam
becomes dangerously buoyant.
Almost like a balloon, the
oil fills the Cofferdam
and makes it rush up
back towards the surface.
The crew members above
are now staring down
a potential disaster
because as the Cofferdam
begins rushing up,
it is heading straight towards
one of the response vessels above.
Thankfully, the crew is able
to get it back under control
with enough time to
direct the Cofferdam away
from the vessel.
Nonetheless, they have to abandon the dam,
which eventually sinks back
down to the bottom of the ocean
where it will remain abandoned.
With this attempt a bust,
there's still no time
for frustration and the
engineers immediately jump back
to the drawing board.
They come up with plan C, the pipe.
For this to work,
they will attempt to siphon
the oil and gas to a tanker,
but this time without a Cofferdam.
Rather, they simply insert a smaller pipe
into the broken well pipe.
And this method actually
works to a degree.
The crew is able to start
collecting some of the oil
in a tank and flare the
natural gas overboard
by diverting it away from the
ship and setting it ablaze.
The oil flow is finally slowed down.
Our measuring container
is filling up slower now,
but it is still steadily increasing
as oil leaks out around the pipe.
And so experts move on yet
again with their next idea,
and they come up with their plan
for the so-called junk shot.
To do this, a very complex procedure
is set up underwater near the well
and a new drilling vessel,
the Q4000 is positioned
above the leak site.
Using this vessel's pipe heavy
drilling mud will be pumped
into the BOP along with
lots of different junk.
This includes anything from
golf balls to rubber tires,
or knotted rope.
The idea is to use the
weight of the mud and junk
to force the oil back down into the well,
so that in a second step,
cement can be poured on top
in order to create a seal.
- It's kinda like stopping up a toilet,
plug up the blowout preventer,
and then at that point,
once we get it plugged up,
we can actually pump
heavy fluids down the well
and hopefully stop it from flowing
and then pump some cement after that.
- [Narrator] With fingers crossed,
crew members start the process.
Mud and junk are shot
into the damaged well,
and using underwater cameras,
crew members monitor the situation.
But yet again, nothing goes to plan,
as they watch the junk
get spewed right back out.
The pressure from the
well is simply too high,
meaning any material dumped
on top is simply displaced
by the gushing oil.
The crew attempts the junk
shot several more times,
but it is a futile effort.
And experts warn that
if they continue trying,
it could lead to instability in the well,
causing what's known as
an underwater blowout.
This would mean that
oil may begin escaping
not just from the well,
but also from many points
throughout the surrounding sea floor.
If this happens, containment
will be virtually impossible,
and so they abandon the junk shot idea,
and suddenly it's back
to square one yet again.
- [News Reporter] Cleanup
is costing $6 million a day,
and when it's all over,
the price will be over a billion dollars.
- [Narrator] With the initial
borehole from plan A still far
from reaching their destination,
the engineers decide to revisit the idea
of a containment dome.
Even though it didn't work
with the original large
Cofferdam, this time they decide
to go for a much smaller,
better fitting cap
that could be installed
directly onto the BOP.
Rather than encasing the
entire area with a large dome,
they could direct the oil flow
straight through this cap,
but there is one issue.
In order to do this, they will
need to cut the damaged pipe
that is still connected to the BOP.
Up until this point, the kinks
in the pipe have been helping
to actually slow the rate
of oil that is leaking out.
And if it is cut off,
the rate of oil escaping
will likely increase
by as much as 20%.
It is an extremely risky move.
If this cap doesn't work,
then they will have made the
situation worse for nothing,
but they have to try.
The decision is made to
cut the damaged pipe off
from the BOP, oil starts
rushing out at a faster pace
than ever before and the clock is ticking.
It takes several days to
situate the new smaller cap
on top of the BOP.
Having learned from the freezing issues
with the previous Cofferdam,
this time warm water is pumped down
to hopefully prevent the
formation of ice crystals.
And as engineers watch the
underwater vehicles at work,
everyone halts their breath
and then with the cap in place,
the oil starts to flow and
everyone sighs with relief
as it actually works.
The cap has created a seal,
and is collecting a
large portion of the oil,
sending it up to a collection
ship on the surface.
In fact, so much oil and gas are collected
that several more vessels are added
for storage and processing,
but the work still isn't done.
Even though this is the most
progress experts have made
in stemming the flow,
they still aren't
capturing all of the leak.
And our container continues to
fill though at a slower rate.
Throughout the next month,
engineers are able to devise,
and install a series
of better fitting caps,
each one lowering the amount
of oil escaping into the sea.
- The story today
is that they're gonna literally
put a new cap, a new top
that may not be the right
nomenclature on the well
that's been leaking in the Gulf of Mexico
for upteen weeks and months or whatever.
- [Narrator] Until finally a
tight enough cap is installed
that is able to completely
stop the oil from leaking
for the first time in three months.
86 days after the initial explosion,
the oil finally stops
leaking into the ocean.
However, tensions are still
high as there is no telling
how long the temporary
capping can hold for.
Luckily though, it does hold
for the time it is needed,
and eventually the first relief
well reaches its destination
intersecting with the original well.
Almost immediately, heavy
mud and cement are now poured
into the bottom of the well
and the news is delivered
to the world that the well has
officially been successfully
and permanently sealed.
110 days after the whole ordeal began.
In the end, approximately
134 million gallons of oil
were lost in the Gulf of Mexico,
filling our container to about 50%.
And this is the figure prominently cited
across a bunch of articles,
and yet this figure
is only a conservative estimate
of how much oil was truly spilled.
A group of independent scientists,
and researchers came together
with their own assessment
and they measured the flow
of oil as seen from videos
of the leak and calculated
effects from pressure,
temperature, geological
conditions, and many other factors.
And according to their estimate,
over 210 million gallons
of oil were actually lost
in the leak.
A massive increase from
the official calculation,
now filling our container up to about 75%.
And this is just a pure crude oil,
though it is important to remember
that every gallon of oil can
coat huge areas of sea surface
as visible by this satellite
image taken by NASA,
showing the oil covered
sea in the Gulf of Mexico.
- [Lisa] We found that the animals
that lived in the near shore environment
had lower survival rates.
We saw 900 plus Dolphins strand,
or wash ashore, many of them dead.
- [Narrator] Bp has heavily
contested this larger figure,
claiming that it doesn't take into account
the hundreds of thousands of
gallons that were siphoned
and collected before it could
enter the Gulf's waters.
Though it is also important to note
that bp has a vested interest
in keeping the figure
as low as possible.
In the end, it is impossible
to know the true exact amount
of how much oil was
lost, but what we do know
is that no matter which of
the two figures you go with,
Deepwater Horizon was the
world's largest accidental spill
to date, with irreputable
damage done to the ecosystem
and the loss of life of
11 men who were working
on the platform when it exploded.
Plugging a hole over
5,000 feet below the ocean
was a massive challenge,
but it's the kind of high stakes problem
only the best engineers can solve.
And for my next video, I focused
on a completely different
kind of engineering marvel,
one that happens much
closer to the surface,
on a racetrack.
As for my upcoming video,
I have animated an
entire Formula 1 pit stop
in order to understand how it's possible
to change all four tires of a race car
in just two and a half seconds.
This video won't be on
YouTube for another month,
but you can already watch it right now
if you have Nebula
On Nebula, I not only
post all my videos early,
but I also post exclusive documentaries
that are not available on YouTube.
For example, I have
made a full length video
about the fascinating
construction of The Twin Towers,
explaining the groundbreaking
new methods used
to build these iconic skyscrapers.
The video is part of my
Nebula original series,
under exposure in which I
explore often overlooked aspects
of topics we all know about.
I've made a video about the
investigation into Flight MH17,
or a video about the Bin Laden Raid
and lots of other topics.
The idea behind Nebula is pretty simple.
It is a platform
that I'm building along a
bunch of other creators,
and since it's a subscription service,
we can use that revenue
to create larger, higher budget projects.
- I get to slip out in the snow tonight.
- Yeah, we bring it on.
- There's no script for this.
- [Narrator] We have a ton
of exclusive documentaries
and we also have Creator run
game shows, comedy specials,
and even feature films.
So go to nebula.tv/neo.
And if you use exactly this link,
you will actually get a 40%
discount of the annual plan,
that comes down to just $3 a
month to access all of Nebula
where you can watch all
my exclusive videos.
So thanks for your support,
and thank you so much for watching.